[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software for software engineering
radio this is Robert bloomin today I am
joined by Bjorn Robin Stein Bjorn is a
production engineer at SoundCloud and
one of the main Prometheus developers
previously he was a site reliability
engineer at Google and a researcher in
the field of molecular modeling yarn
welcome to software engineering radio
welcome thanks for having me it's great
to have you today yarn and I will be
discussing site reliability engineering
and since I'll be saying that a lot I
will often say SR e if you hear s re
then that's what I meant we will be
discussing the arts experience and also
many ideas from the book site
reliability engineering how Google runs
production systems which came out
earlier this year yarn would you like to
say anything to the listeners about your
background that I didn't already cover
um yeah kind of you got my life in a
nutshell so I mean I had two jobs in my
life like to conventional employments
the one is the current at SoundCloud
which I'm after my three-year
anniversary tomorrow actually which is
kind of neat and before that I had like
7 and of 8 years at Google as a central
liability engineer as you said and
previously I was just doing freelancing
in the I don't know alaikum bubble or
something but originally I'm a scientist
so originally I wanted to just do the
proper scientific research not computer
science like real science for some
reason I got stuck there and and
that up in computing anyway yarn I've
been working in the field of DevOps for
about a year now but I've been hearing
that term for six or seven years we have
already done two shows on that topic
number 247 and 268 on infrastructure as
code I recommend those to the listener
as background to this show in the last
year I started hearing a term sre he's
sre another name for DevOps or is there
more to it than that
but that's a really good question like I
think I mean definitely the term sre was
invented at Google internally way
earlier I think DevOps is like 2008 or
something the birth of the term you have
to correct me if I'm wrong and I'm not
sure when they came up with the term as
early at Google I think Ben trainer who
is kind of the head of the whole
department was hired in 2003 so I was
interviewed in 2005 and joined the
company 2006 so I was already history in
a way so the term existed before and I
still remember I was kind of glad when
this term DevOps appeared because I
could finally explain to people what I'm
doing like I thought this is actually a
neat explanation right I'm kind of a
DevOps type at Google but then I realize
it's causing even more confusion and I
think that's not so much because there's
such a difference between SOA and and
therefore as terms it's more like that
DevOps covers so many things like people
understand a lot of different things
when they say DevOps so I guess you have
treated that in the previous shows IIIi
don't know them by detail so can't say
but to be like a bit mean I think many
people if they say DevOps they basically
mean okay we have depth and we have ops
and now they should get along well with
each other and we call that divorce
which is obviously probably not what it
should be but its overall to be very
different from the Google as a review on
the other hand like especially now that
I'm at sound
well we we have a particular approach to
develops which is more like yeah we
don't really have theirs dedicated devs
and dedicated offs we are both like
everybody is both in a way right and
that's another interpretation of their
verbs which is probably not what many
people mean when they say it and it's
also different from what Google means if
they say yes Ari yeah so I guess there's
an overlap and they they phrased it
quite nicely in the book in the
introduction there's a little box pretty
much in the beginning where they explain
the relationship between their forms and
SRE
I mean I guess we can discuss it in a
bit more detail that perhaps that
answers your initial question yes it
does we have as you guess done some
basic shows on DevOps that covered a lot
of ground and I think your answer
encapsulates that there may not be a
complete agreement among everyone using
these terms what they mean I'd like to
focus because of this book and your
experience how does Google define sre
and what is their take on it that is a
bit different from the rest of the
industry so I think there wasn't really
a one-line definition the like as I said
I was so glad when there was a term like
that once a catchy term you can tell
people if they're asked what you're
doing and in the book itself they
actually also discuss how difficult it
was to explain to outsiders auditories
and now we have the book that we can
just tell them read the world it's no
one line explanation right there's a
whole book around it
obviously you want something shorter I
guess so I had this one line I think it
was Jamie Wilkinson who is an SRE at
Google who is very much into monitoring
we might talk about that later and I
listened to a talk because it was about
monitoring and he said that in the
introduction essary is if you take
software engineers and let them design
an operational function something like
that right so you your and I think this
is important to understand that SOE is
in a way it's a dedicated ops team the S
or
Nazeri team but their use of engineering
techniques to approach the problem of
ops right so perhaps that catches it and
I think in the asari book in that box
they say you could say s re is a
particular implementation of DevOps with
some peculiarities but in general you
could say that it's a specific kind of
DevOps yeah so perverse that catches a
bit of it ok you're now talking about
sres apply a software development
discipline to the problem of ops what
type of software do s eries develop and
how is it different than what we think
of as the application yeah that's also a
very good question
of course like where's the line like in
practice I think in a way as a red shirt
be involved in the ideal case in the
development of the application already
because as always know how to like run
that application at scale in the
maintainable fashion so they they
certainly should have contributions
there or if it goes wrong like I've seen
that as well that that like you there is
a product developed it's launched and it
just isn't sustainable in operation
right and then basically SRS come back
to you and try to fix it but I mean
ideally that's already taken care of
when you're launch on the other hand
there's a lot of code you're right I
mean it's this infamous replace yourself
if the shawl is small shell script but
in practice obviously the shell script
is not really small and it's probably
also not a shell script all the time I
mean I've seen shell script mutations at
Google as well but that's that's more an
anti-pattern right if it's getting too
complicated you don't take a very big
shell script you take Python or even
another language whatever there are so
many things where you can just automate
yourselves out of your job essentially
so whenever something you do it three
times and it's redundant and it's stupid
and you should ask the machines to do it
and that's software development in a way
but then there are also there
like software I would call
infrastructure software where the line
gets really blurry I mean let's say you
want to develop a cluster management
software or you want to develop a
monitoring system and at Google
there were dedicated software
engineering teams that developed that
software and they might have had an SRE
team again so there's again this line or
even the infrastructure development is
is not per se sree but then the line
gets buried like for example my team I
was in at Google they just happened to
develop a kind of distributed cron which
was totally infrastructure software but
then it happened that the SRE team
developed that software so it's it's a
blurry line and if you if you go outside
of Google where you're out smaller
scales it's it's even more much blurrier
and and that's how cloud the world looks
completely different so I've seen
different worlds there but yeah it's
it's in practice sometimes you draw the
line quite clearly and sometimes it's
really an overlap I'm gonna come back to
SoundCloud a bit later but for now I'd
like to stick with Google one of the
main themes in the book was the way
Google balances development work with
operational and on-call work for its
sre how did they do that so to again try
to find a one line thing I guess that
would be the 50% rule which also applies
to many other organization or should
should apply essentially if you're doing
more than 50% of operational work in
your your your work life you are already
in a non-sustainable state so the the
rule was as necessary you should be able
to use at least 50% of your time if it's
more even even better on like automating
tasks reducing tech depth get yourself
out of the whole your view of doc before
and and at most 50 percent would be time
spent on call or just fighting fires
fixing things that just broke right and
the idea by that is if you your system
usually
Crow's right I mean if you have a
healthy business Google or not you you
want like 2 X 3 X 4 X growth every year
and you never grow your engineering
population by that factor right so if
you have doing 50 percent operational
work next year you will do hundred
percent operational work and so you are
completely there and another year later
you will do 200 percent operational work
it like you're running 60 hours a week
or something I don't know and then you
burn out and you give up and and that's
the end of your business if I try to
synthesize what it is you're saying and
this book is saying about s sorry if I
think of generation 0 and our awareness
of these systems you'd build an
application you give it to some guys and
tell them to deploy it and figure out
how to run it and generation one is you
start getting feedback from ops that you
take into account during development sre
is where the operational needs are fully
integrated into the lifecycle of
software for the organization would that
be a fair statement I guess you could
but it might also depend on like in a
pure Google view it probably depends on
your situation like back in my days I
don't know if that's more elaborated
these days back in my days having every
support for your product like as a
development team
you really wanted as a resupport for
your product that was highly sought
after because there were so few referees
relative to let's say classical software
engineers so like core products like
search and ads and Gmail there had for
sure as a resort but if you were like
launching something more niche then you
would be probably completely in charge
as a developer for running and deploying
that product as well once you have that
essary support I guess you have this
kind of team that deals with things like
like deploying I mean there's also
release engineering at Google I'm also
not sure now
that I've been away from there for three
years how that developed which plays
with each other but yeah like it's in a
way where you say let's say one flavor
of the Arabs were developers are just
very very close to deployment and and do
it themselves or something that would
definitely be a slightly different
approach from let's say a Google
large-scale core product yeah you're
also our bit conservative
if you run like if you make $2,000 a
second you don't just want to push a
button and then everything goes down and
you say oops let's roll back sure
requires some thought in advance how
you're gonna keep that revenue stream
going DevOps may be a good description
of what people are doing or the roots of
the discipline the term sre contains the
word reliability that is a another focus
of the book I wanted you to give me your
take on Dickerson's hierarchy of
reliability yeah yeah that's a great one
so diggers in this Mikey Dickerson and
the listeners might know him he is the
person who runs the humorous digital
services that's the right name at home I
hope I got that right he was actually
the head of my sister team like I wasn't
Dublin in an Adsense or a team and we
had a sister team over there in
California and he was heading that team
so we had we had a lot of collaboration
and at some point he moved on and I mean
it's a longer story he told that story
quite often now he is there at the White
House at the u.s. digital services which
is kind of an SRE team for the US
government if you're on right and funny
enough if i remember that correctly only
when he had to explain all those
principles that were in our DNA he came
up with this hierarchy of reliability
and that that's modeled after the
hierarchy of needs by who was that guy
this like Smashville
exactly the psychologist which is all
about like like the most noble human
activities essentially the
of the pyramid and you can't like do
self-actualization if you if you don't
feed yourself and if you don't feed
yourself even like being safe doesn't
matter right it's this whole hierarchy
where the most basic ones are actually
the most important ones and they are at
the bottom and and in the pyramid
they're the the huge things and then you
put the smaller and more delicate things
on top and so my key created that
hierarchy for reliability and the bottom
layer is the one I always remember
because it's monitoring which is my
personal let's say special area as a
Prometheus developer but that was also
were like at SoundCloud where you come
into this this growing company that runs
into this problem with with like running
a growing more and more complex system
in a reliable fashion and the first like
you you use you you realize it's
monitoring and without monitoring
nothing else works looking at a picture
of Dickerson's hierarchies monitoring is
the bottom most layer of that yeah and
then I mean I have the picture as well
now that we're talking about it
Nexus I don't know it by heart right I
stopped at monitoring but anyway Nexus
incident response which like argue is
really closely connected and then you
have like a post mortem and thing root
case case analysis I just remember like
the whole thing whole idea of blameless
post mortems
because that's I think in many
traditional companies there's a lot of
scaring people and and blame them if
something happens that's like a very
important thing at Google that you're of
this mistakes are to be learned from and
not not to fire somebody and then it
goes on testing and release procedures
that we all we talked about that
capacity planning development and then
the tip is the product itself right I
mean this is the one thing that people
outside see and they think this is
everything but in reality it's
essentially the tip of the iceberg
frenched and correctly the parallel to
Maslow's hierarchy you can't take care
of the higher levels you cannot achieve
the higher lows and
till you've solidified all of the lower
levels and foundation in each one
enables you to proceed to the next level
and Dickerson is observing the same kind
of dependencies exist between these
layers in the reliability world exactly
exactly and that's interesting if like
if you even back then when I joined
Google I was kind of getting into this
Wonderland of science fiction I don't
know like ten years time off I'm now ten
years in the future and I see how
computing is done in the future
but like if you if you have this I mean
Mikey had this in an extreme fashion I
think it's called brownfield or your
enter I feel that it's already pretty
established but calm cope with the
modern challenges and then you have to
explain to people and you have to build
it up from the base right and you start
with monitoring
I guess SoundCloud and my experience was
less brownfield because it is a pretty
young and yeah modern organization but
monitoring like it grew into this higher
larger scale a lot of users a lot of
complexity and then monitoring was
definitely the TAFE the grounds to yeah
having a reliable site and then you
build up you put one layer on top of
another yeah it does make sense to me
when I look at it because without
monitoring you have no knowledge of what
the system is doing if you have
monitoring you need to respond when
something goes wrong otherwise it won't
get fixed then after the fact you need
to do post-mortem
to understand why and next layer is
testing you need to have test to prevent
that same bug or similar bugs from
getting back into production this is all
making sense to me maybe when we get to
the next layer capacity planning do you
have a clear idea why that is the next
layer above testing I don't laugh a
spontaneous clear idea right now but I
mean that I guess that's a pretty high
level function right I mean the if
you're if your site is on fire all the
time and
every deploy breaks everything you don't
even think about capacity planning so it
might also be something you only think
about that I mean it's super important
of course like every step in the
hierarchy and arguably the topmost one
is the most important because your
product is what why you're doing all of
that but you can only even think about
it once the other things are there right
so capacity planning is like once your
monitoring is in place you can start to
collect metrics like long term and then
you can start to think about capacity
planning you can start to project you
understand your system how it's going
out scaling and and only then you can
start with meaningful capacity planning
I found in the book very interesting
discussion
there are ways of measuring reliability
and this question will not be so much
about measurement let's assume we can
measure reliability by uptime or error
rate the point was that you need to
decide how much reliability you want or
you want to pay for and there is such a
thing as too much reliability what do
they mean by that at Google and they
talk about having too much reliability
yeah so I mean the one thing I have this
quite often not only at Google and
perhaps even more so like outside of it
when I talk to people who haven't seen
that when you start to set an SLO like I
mean not yet an SL a like you you are
not signing a contract now you will find
out what am i aiming for do you define
those two terms SLO and SLA so SLI is
this service level agreement so that's
essentially a like legal contract or
it's an internal within the company
contract where you say okay we're we're
serving at this level of whatever
availability reliability through port
that's what we commit to and if we break
it I mean between like different
entities you might be legally liable but
like this is the contract right the SLR
or something
you aim for this is what we set as our
objective and then I mean the SL I is
the service level indicator thing that's
that's the first thing when you even
define what you are doing to measure
your service level and then you have the
objective to know what you're aiming for
what you're designing your system for
and then as the last step you agree okay
this is our system and we formally agree
to keep that service level and so the
objectives that's the part where you
could aim too high right like people
naively think like the more reliable a
services the better but then you might
over engineer right if you go for an
approach we'll say okay just give me the
light and see as low as possible and
give me as many nines as possible you
this will influence your design all
right you get to a point where you're
over engineer the system and you invest
too much efforts and you also you reduce
your agility in a way right and that's
the other term where that probably often
plays a role is this error budgeting
where you say I mean that's also in the
relationship between an SRE team and a
developer team you tell them it's
actually fine to only have three nines
or four nines because that's our ass
alone right and you have a narrow budget
you can play you can do a risky deploys
to try something out as long as we keep
our error budget and once you reach your
error budget then like okay no no that's
that's it we have to do more
conservative from now on and we cannot
just do a risky deploys so it's actually
it's it's worth something to be able to
do risky things that might create errors
you also get an advantage from that and
that's what it's really important to
have an objective and I had a very
practical thing that sounded like my
first project at songcraft was actually
suffering from a misunderstanding of the
SLO so we designed the whole system
because ans are over set like every
crest has to be served in a hundred
milliseconds right and then we decide
the old system and a way to do that and
it had 10 times larger a resource
footprint that it could have been so
later another kind of the same service
was implemented again with a different
SLO in mined and used wireless resource
because it had a different SLO right so
it really matters it's not just better
it's not always better in a way yeah
we've been talking a lot about the
Google experience in the Google book
you're also you're now currently at
SoundCloud what did you bring from the
sre philosophy that you're able to apply
in your current position at SoundCloud
yeah it's it's kind of fascinating how
much it actually is I only realized that
when I when that book came out because I
mean there's on the testimonials page
like the very first page you can see a
quote of myself how I kind of praised
the book as my gospel that I'm preaching
at work I mean it's it's I was surprised
because the setup is so different and
and the whole organization is so
different so we are totally not an SRE
team we are doing quite different things
but there's so many lessons you could
still still apply and it's nice draft
it's all codified and I realize how much
of those lessons I have applied at
SoundCloud so it's I don't even know
where to start
but it's yeah it's interesting how you
can use those little concepts and ideas
even in a pretty pretty different setup
why don't you pick one example of a
sorry concept that you successfully
applied at SoundCloud yeah I mean I'm
totally biased you always talk about
monitoring okay it's the the basis of
the reliability permit on reliability
hierarchy according to Mikey that was
even before I joined sauerkraut there
were a bunch of X Google s arrays that
joint SoundCloud for some reason at the
same time it was not even coordinated it
just happened and their first big
problem was indeed monitoring like this
indeed wasn't wasn't met they had no
idea where to even start or to what we
see what's going on and I mean that
wasn't only felt by them but by
everybody sound of us getting more
complex they started this micro service
thing and and things started to scale up
and getting complicated and no
we had an inside what's actually going
on here and so that was for them the
reason to start even a monitoring
project which is Prometheus right so
that they could get monitoring in a way
they knew from Google and and that would
allow them to you have to apply even the
principles of of site reliability
engineering and perhaps one thing we
might talk about on call because that's
probably something that many people run
into traditional approaches of alerting
is like a server is down like I set up
my nog yours check and if the server
doesn't ping anymore I like somebody up
- to reboot it or something right you
you just now mentioned on call for
listeners who are not as saris toss
about what on call is as part of a sorry
job description so on call obviously if
you on call your carrier pager you get
alerts from the machines if they need
you if they need you an intervention an
SRE team at Google is usually doing the
like first level on call support for
their product so let's say if you're on
a desert back in my days there was
actually we were on call for everything
that had ads it got later when every
everything grew bigger we had like more
specialized teams for developers that's
great because they they get first level
support for their product developers
still are like on call in a secondary or
tertiary position or like if the SRA
can't deal with the problem they might
get woken up but it's definitely
something that's pretty crucial for SOA
at the same time remember the 50% rule
you are never supposed to invest more
than 50% of your time into those
operational concerns also SRS are not
paid your monkeys that's a common
misunderstanding also paralyzes
parallels therefore ops misunderstanding
I think when when you think yeah if we
have our DevOps team entire page on
monkeys right so it's it's a bit smarter
than that but yeah you are definitely on
called as an important part of the job
okay
and I interrupted you
our discussion of how this came about at
SoundCloud you were setting up on call
yeah that's that's the example were
monitoring and on call place into each
other so we were there where you
basically get get a page if a single
server dies and and your monitoring
system mirrors that that idea right
because you have your Nagios probe that
pings the server if the server goes down
you get a page so now your scale and you
have thousands of servers they might not
even be physical servers they might be
in the cloud and virtual machines or
whatnot and then at some point you
realize if I've wake somebody up
whenever a server dies I will wake
somebody up all the time
and that's something that is not
sustainable and you can't just solve it
by having coming back to that a team of
Pedro monkeys that I just paid for
getting paged all the time
you also have already designed your
system probably in a way that it can
sustain single host failure for example
right so there's where you get into an
area where you start to think okay so
when should I actually wake up a human
being it's like it's this metaphor where
like the computers essentially the
normal mortal beings and and they they
call the superheroes if they can't cope
right so and the superheroes are the
humans that that get paged
so one should a machine called a human
in for emergency and and then you start
thinking okay I need I need a different
view I cannot just think about okay a
machine has failed that's probably a
problem I have to look at something like
it's my user experience affected because
if I have a nice cluster management
solution a distributed system that might
perfectly cope with single machine
failures my user experience is fine
right at some point of course somebody
should check out what's going on with
that machine but that can be during work
hours
forever right I don't have to wake
somebody up to erect within two or three
minutes so you get into this idea of
what we call symptom based alerting so
you alert if if something is wrong with
you user experience or something is
imminent to go wrong with your user
experience that's that's the best case
when you know for sure it will happen
but it hasn't happened yet and the other
thing is the the course based alerting
where you think okay a machine goes down
that might be a reason for a possible
failure or a wreck switch is broken or
something right where you were you alert
on something that might or might not be
the problem in the end like causing a
problem and that's for example a very
different paradigm how to alert want to
wake up evil and now we come back to the
hierarchies of reliability you need this
basic level of monitoring your
monitoring system must be able to tell
you that right if your monitoring system
is only able to tell you that a machine
doesn't think anymore you will not be
able to set something up like that yeah
and one interject here you mentioned
Prometheus monitoring we do have a show
recorded on Prometheus it hasn't been
published yet at the time I'm recording
this show I believe it will be 270 but
anyone who'd like to learn more
specifically about Prometheus you can
find it on the se radio website you've
been talking a lot about what should be
monitored about monitoring at different
layers of the stack different types of
performance in the book they discussed
the concept of googles for golden
signals what are the four signals and
why are they very critical things to
monitor so yes so they they mentioned
those four goals he notes in the book
it's like we can read it like the Bible
chapter six I mean there are two exactly
there are different opinions
what like the most important things to
monitor are but but there's a huge
overlap even if there are like different
opinions in detail you will always come
back if you ask the experts if there
there's a common core right we can just
take them from the book and the four
golden signals and actually have it here
my Bible is always with me so the first
one is latency so how long does it take
to to server requests then your of
traffic that's how many requests you're
serving and
errors are how many of them result in an
error and then saturation is how fool
your service is meaning what's actually
your capacity I mean you might be
serving quite fine right now but if you
increase your traffic by 10% you might
start to fail and and then you you think
about redundancy and that's of course
also important for capacity planning but
also like if you if you have the luxury
of multiple data centers globally how do
you route traffic when do you decide
that that you not have not enough
redundancy now and you should do do
should do something
can you can you afford to just send a
data center into maintenance right now
things like that so saturation that
could be at any level for example we
could have CPU saturation or on a single
instance or i/o saturation on a
particular storage device all the way up
to what you think is a high level
measure of capacity of larger system
yeah also track for the profane how
foolish you disk right I ask you how did
you apply sre concepts from Google at
Sound Cloud were there things you tried
to apply from Google that it turns out
they didn't work at Sound Cloud because
it's a different job and different
organization conditions are different
yeah so those Paul's four I would say
was mostly not a technical thing like
like technical ideas from the essary
world almost always apply to other like
if you're at a minimum scale things just
apply it's it's like a natural law but
there's a huge organizational and let's
say cultural thing about it I I said
before how much sought-after sre support
at Google was so people developer teams
really wanted SRS so that gave them bit
of let's say authority they could say
okay if we support your service users
has to behave in a certain way and if it
doesn't behave that way
then we want
for it or we will give the pager and
things like that happened and that's in
a way it empowers you and that set up
wasn't just there at SoundCloud for one
like the scale of SoundCloud although we
scale a lot of traffic and surf a lot of
features is is so different you couldn't
have a dedicated S or a team for every
let's say product we have right
SoundCloud is two orders of magnitude
smaller in terms of engineering
population than and something like
Google or Facebook but we don't have two
orders of magnitude fewer products right
perhaps you have a tenth of the products
right but it's like you still have a
customer facing thing a billing thing
something for the users all those things
are there even in at a smaller scale and
you cannot just have a dedicated as a
routine just for ads right so the ratios
are different you might be a hundred
times less on some scales but ten times
less on other scales so you can't have
the same ratios consistent throughout
with what you see at Google yeah that
makes a big difference and in this
concrete example we couldn't just say oh
we are building up an S or a team now
and the SRA team will take your pager
for the whole company right so that just
wasn't feasible and in in Reverse that
means there was nothing where the s
origin could say okay if you're not
doing it this and that way we will just
not take the picture because they were
not going to take the patron right
so then I think that was before my time
they try to like let's say okay we have
proper s eries but they are like
embedded in in the smaller teams we have
like we sent an SRE into this team and
they should use their magic wand to make
everything a reliable and that didn't
really work either
they were also already an established
culture how things were done and it is
like you cannot just like your culture
is usually also it's there for a reason
and it's precious and you cannot just
change everything to it to a different
color
sure I mean not at least if there's yeah
I guess there needed to be like this for
need that you need to change the culture
for some reason because it's
dysfunctional but it wasn't this one's
not sound right we had a precious
culture and in the end things worked out
quite differently in some way nowadays
everybody at SoundCloud is an SRE in a
way because we follow this approach
where what I said in the beginning the
devs are also ops you build it you run
it so what happened in the end is not
that we build up a dedicated Azeri team
that would work like a Google s or a
team but it was more like that we
fostered s re approaches throughout the
engineering organization and now
everybody is no way a little less re in
the company you're talking about the
relationship between the SRE team or
maybe the s re role if it's not a team
and and development in this negotiation
about who who is gonna carry the pager
who owns alerts how do you find the
right division of responsibilities
within an organization between what goes
to s re and what goes to developers so
the Google approach if you have the
properly supported s re supported
service then all the all the alerts go
to s Ari's first right and and for
important services they might have a
secondary rotation in case a page faults
through but only then there's the
tertiary on-call where the developer is
paged and ideally a page never falls
through automatically it's just that
that the SOE if there's something where
think okay this is somebody changed
something in the code and I don't
understand it and and now I really need
a particular developer then you page the
developers it in my case in my personal
case we were in Europe in Dublin and and
were in charge of way more
different little products than then the
corresponding team in California because
we were the smaller team we were
covering more while they were asleep and
we had a lot of different developer
teams that we needed to escalate to if
needed ideally not of course we would be
able to handle it on our own
but again that's at smaller scales like
SoundCloud scale that's just not going
to happen so it sound cloud there is
essentially our team called Production
Engineering not site reliability
engineering we don't carry the picture
for any product we carry the picture for
the systems we are in charge of directly
like let's say cluster management
monitoring infrastructure stuff and then
but whatever you develop whatever you
build you'll run it you're also on call
for it so it's a completely different
layout of responsibilities I was
recently at a talk by gene Kim who's one
of the leading thinkers and writers in
the DevOps space
he posted a slide which said when we
started paging developers at 2:00 a.m.
problems got fixed very quickly now that
sounds a little bit cynical and maybe
manipulative but is that is that a good
way for sre in development to work
together I mean if you if you have to
apply that pressure it's I guess I would
hate it like from a personal perspective
but I think there are three different
scenarios we have now here in the
discussion the one is essentially what
that expression is referring to you have
an existing engineering organization you
have like ops people that get paid all
the time because developers deploy
software thrown over the wall and and it
doesn't work right and then you think
okay we just page the developers at 2:00
a.m. and then they will fix it
at at Google it's the corresponding
situation is probably that a software it
doesn't really work according to
standards and then the answer is as a
last resort can threaten to give back
the pager and and stop to support that
system at Sound Cloud I was again a
different different setup
that kind of patriarchy thing I think
they might have tried it one one point
but it really didn't exist when I came
there it was really humility run it was
already reality so people had more the
opposite problem that we had two small
teams that shared an on-call rotation
because they got really in love with
their software and and you had like two
or three people that were the only one
that knew about that particular service
and they were doing the on-call so
essentially a person was on call
whatever Monday to wednesday and the
other person was on call Thursday
through Sunday and and they had no life
anymore but it was their software they
knew everything about it that was kind
of the it was doing it wrong in the
other direction were where the
developers were too closely related to
that which couldn't really happen in a
Google style a story set up because
there your hand over you support to an
SRE team so you must be sure everything
is documented nicely there was a
reasonably smart engineers but they have
to learn what's going on here so you
kind of are forced to make it
approachable for others and it's out of
a small the problem that this didn't
work at all
but that has changed like we improved a
lot there that that now we have bigger
encore rotations people transfer that
knowledge to other people so more people
are capable to deal with a certain
outage in a certain service yeah and
this is something that is necessary for
an organization to scale is that the
knowledge has to be transferred and
shared among more people you did just
now mention documentation talk about the
role of documentation in in sharing
operational knowledge yeah that's that's
definitely a hot topic
starting from designing a new product or
a new iteration on an existing one
google has a really strong culture of
writing design Docs reviewing design
Docs in an informal fashion like we had
a design dog reading club in Dublin
but it's also formal review of design
dogs and SoundCloud was much more in the
way I don't know agile capital a or not
was more like okay let's just do it
which came from this start of culture
were you really a small group of people
everybody knew each other and liked
sharing information was not an issue and
then you grow into a bigger organization
and this is also I guess something or
SoundCloud has matured a lot and after a
few incidents that were caused by not
having shared information enough or
starting to develop something without
asking that other person two floors down
that would actually have known a lot
about that particular problem and we
have a way better yeah sharing culture
let's say we write I don't think we call
it our C's and not not design Docs but
it's essentially a similar thing so
that's from the start on and then of
course operational documentation is
really important that's also something
where your monitoring system to come
back to that again can help you
for example we we have a nice way of
displaying a documentation link with an
alert like you get an alert it might be
that alert of that sister team you are
now on call for because they're only two
people but they the alert already gives
you a link to their run books so what's
what's going on if that fires what's the
background and and what what can I do to
handle that situation and that was also
that's also very similar to Google
despite the complete different in
structure we had also a really strong
culture of having alerting documentation
for incidents
he just now used this term run book
where if I understand if I'm on call I
get an alert that the the fubar is down
and here's a link to the run book which
is documentation site and it would say
check the queue length make sure the
database is running look in the error
log if you see this in this try
restarting those type of things is that
what a run book is yes pretty much I
think in the SOE book they call it
playbook so there again different words
for essentially the same thing I also
like to have to write down run books
because that's kind of litmus test if
your response is essentially scriptable
if your run book is yeah that happens
all the time just turn it off and on
again restart that service that's a
clear hint for okay perhaps you can
actually put that into a software and
let the machines do it and don't wake up
a human being while if you see this is
actually a guideline for an intelligent
response right where you see okay I
actually have to use my common sense and
my intelligence to find out what's going
on here then it's a good run book right
I mean the run book you can't blame the
red book if if you have set up something
where the run book is a script you
should turn it into a script that's
essentially the lesson sure that very
much goes along with the theme in the
book which they call removing toil and
by another name automate all the things
yo okay Joran well we've talked a lot
about Google's approach and how it can
or can't be applied elsewhere suppose
I'm a bit of a skeptic and I say this
would be great if we had all this money
and all these people to develop all
these operational systems but
organizations don't all have the same
resources as Google and it may be
difficult to get their head above water
and focus on automating things because
everything's breaking all the time how
can the organization that
sees themselves as not being like Google
at all what can they apply from the
Google philosophy I mean I guess
SoundCloud is a pretty good case study
for exactly that problem so sauerkraut
has a hundred something engineers I
don't know the exact number right now
but it's if you know like the tech scene
and you know like how many engineers
let's say typical competitors of
SoundCloud have you would be surprised
how small the organization is not much
they get done but so we we're definitely
in that situation where we are resource
wise or resource is a very general term
including humans where we have not a lot
to spend and we still have to keep the
system running and we we were pretty
much in that state where the the old
approach like you can read that
everywhere monolithic Ruby on Rails
application for the site it just didn't
scale in various Y so something had to
be done the decision was to go micro
services and that's you've really bold
to do like under full steam so that took
a lot of it was just a lot of work to do
and and at the same time there's
constant pressure to launch new features
because it's a hard competition so you
have exactly what you were thinking
about I guess
so what what can we even do like our
site is falling apart all the time we
have new features to launch you have new
infrastructure to to implement and yeah
still we kind of pulled it off we have
we are pretty reliable by now so what's
what's the I think it's difficult to
just give a rule of thumb or what you
can do we course of course you you as an
engineer I say I just push back if if
like I'm asked to implement the next big
feature and I think we have way too much
tech that I mean you have to push back I
guess but sometimes there's just a
business need if you don't implement
that feature we out of business so yeah
it's hard but I guess you need to make
yourself hurt so that you have the right
you you way of all the things you have
to take into account and and come to the
right decision but like dying of tech
depth is definitely something that can
easily happen and I guess for people
outside of an engineering organization
it's really hard to realize they see
engineering as a black box they can't
know what's going on and you have to
explain that quite carefully that you
need some air to get out of this 50%
trap right when the 50% oil become
humble present and then to 1% and then
there's just no way back like you should
try if you go over the 50% you should
you should really try hard to get the
way out of that and yeah it might be
hard but like in this outdoor case we
have proven it's it's possible yeah and
I do want to mention show 2:24 we did
about technical debt which addresses
some of those issues now Bjorn for last
question before we start wrapping up you
and I were chatting offline about you
have a background in molecular science
and I'm working in the sre or DevOps
field I had my education in physics and
one of my co-workers also had a physics
background you said it's not uncommon to
meet people in the sre world who have a
non-conventional background meaning I
suppose outside of computer science do
you have any thoughts on why that might
be
yeah that's something I've found like
what what I like I'd never applied
myself at Google like I would not have
dared it was like okay this is what
computer science graduates from Stanford
to or something but then once I was
inside I realized okay so there are like
a lot of physicists chemists like myself
or like historians or people who have
never studied anything and I just turned
out that they have the talent and of
course I mean they had brought also some
experience but I think I mean what
recruiters always told me it's so hard
to hire for sree because you you want
this software engineering mindset
combined with yeah I'm totally not
afraid of thinking about network packets
or whatever running a script or I don't
know like like half
this this combined skillset of a
software engineer that also is kind of
assist at mini type and has all those
things in their DNA as well and I could
imagine I mean that's pure speculation
if you're coming from let's say you do
this physics or chemistry thing that
that you you are more likely to develop
those skills like in my case I was I'm a
biochemist and we happen to do like
simulations and we needed a lot of
computing power and the university was
like didn't have a lot of budget so we
start to build back then in the 90s like
a big evolved computing cluster and that
started with okay we don't even have
like technicians that would help us
assemble that thing so we now have to go
to shops and get like three offers from
different shops and then build it all
together and then the the Linux network
drivers were a bit problematic with a
lot of traffic back then or whatever
like so you started to do everything the
like I think nowadays the buzzword is
full stack so you are actually a
physicist or a chemist but you start to
buy computer hardware and hack kernel
drivers and then in the end you'll also
write the software that runs the
simulation and you have this whole view
and also you have to present results in
the end at a conference and perhaps
that's a nice like education or it
sharpens your mind for what you need in
an SRE setting your is there anywhere on
the web where listeners could go if they
would like to learn more about you yeah
just Google me I guess I mean I don't
have I don't exist kind of because I
don't have a Twitter handle
but like recently with the with
Prometheus becoming so popular the
Prometheus folks get invited to
conferences a lot so and I think my name
is pretty unique on the Internet
there might be one or two others with
that name but I guess I'm more popular
than them so you can listen to loads of
talks about Prometheus or also like we
there was as a recon in Dublin this year
I
gave the last talk nice talk about
alerting that pretty much resonates with
the topics we covered here so yeah
definitely
you can find a lot about that great yarn
thank you so much for speaking to
software engineering radio alright thank
you - thank you listeners for
downloading the show you can send us
feedback multiple ways you can direct
message us on Twitter at se radio on our
Facebook group or LinkedIn group or
email us team at se - radio net for
software engineering radio this has been
Robert blumen getting software to your
users quickly and reliably is the most
important part of being a software
engineer snap C is cloud-based
continuous integration and continuous
deployment tool lets you set up in
minutes with your github account and
within a few clicks we'll have your
first pipeline running discover and fix
your bugs quickly before pushing the
production by setting up stages from
simple ones to complex that run
automatically when you push your changes
need more speed run tests in parallel
with expanded workers and get your
feedback fast deploy to Heroku AWS and
more we even integrate with slack to
give you updates on your builds go to
snap CI slash software radio and build
test and deploy free for 30 days
snap CI embodies the lessons the thought
works has learned from 20 years of
software deployment the same lessons
that have been written about by Martin
Fowler and J's humble check it out at
snap CI slash software radio thanks for
listening to se Radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can write
comments on each episode on the website
or write a review on iTunes mention a
message us on Twitter at se radio or
search for the software engineering
radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us a team at se - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]